Guide to the Connecticut State University System Records RG 1.CG.01
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Connecticut State University System Records
1965-2004
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Connecticut State University (System).
RG 1.CG.01
3.5 Linear Feet, 3 boxes
The Connecticut State University System dates back to 1849. Colleges in the system all began as teachers colleges and gradually were given responsibility for educational programs such as liberal arts, business, technology, and health services. They were brought together into a state college system in 1965, and were granted university status in 1983.
Provenance
Administrative transfer.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The history of the Connecticut State University System dates back to 1849 when the New Britain Normal School, the oldest public institution of higher education in Connecticut, was founded. Other teachers colleges were later established in Willimantic (1889), New Haven (1893), and Danbury (1903). In addition to teacher education the four colleges gradually were given responsibility for educational programs such as liberal arts, business, technology, and health services. They were brought together into a state college system in 1965, and were granted university status in 1983.
The Board of Trustees for the Connecticut State University System is responsible for the governance of the four universities under its jurisdiction: Central Connecticut State University in New Britain, Eastern Connecticut State University in Willimantic, Southern Connecticut State University in New Haven, and Western Connecticut State University in Danbury. The Board determines the general policy of the university system, reviews and approves institutional budget requests, sets tuition and fees, and appoints the chancellor of the system and the university presidents.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of reports and publications generated by the Connecticut State University System. The records are divided into 10 series: 1. Board of Trustees, 2. Chancellor's Office, 3. Office of the President, 4. Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs and Research, 5. Office of Finance and Management. 6. Office of Institutional Research and Planning, 7. Connecticut State University System Foundation, 8. Connecticut State University System Research Foundation, 9. Office of Public Relations, 10. Connecticut State University Publications, and 11. University Wide Committee on the Arts.
Series 1 contains the Board of Trustees agendas for board meetings, mission statements and Policy Books for the CSU System. Researchers should search the CSUS website, www.ctstate.edu, for additional information concerning the Board of Trustees and the CSU System.
Series 2 contains information originating from the Governmental Relations office that advises the Chancellor on legislative and regulatory matters. This series consists mainly of financial reports but also contains correspondence on the administrative space needs for WCSU during 1995. This series also contains two strategic planning reports by Coopers & Lybrand summarizing CSUS' needs and recommendations for a long-term information technology strategy, and a final report on how CSUS, and its four constituent universities, could improve administrative practices.
Series 3 contains very little information other than an invitation to Dallas K. Beal's inauguration in 1985, and a memo sent to the CSUS community announcing Beal's retirement.
Series 4 contains a copy of the Directory of Faculty Scholarly & Research Expertise. This directory does not contain all of the University's faculty members, or all of the faculty actively engaged in research, but does contain what is felt to be a representative group from the combined faculties on the four campuses of CSUS.
The information contained in Series 5 is relatively small but is representative of the CSUS budgets presented to the state legislature. The Office of Finance and Management, has system wide responsibility for accounting, reporting, financial systems, planning and budgeting (operating and capital), accounts receivable/payable, purchasing, receiving, payroll, inventory control, capital projects, and facilities management.
The Fact Books, published by Office of Institutional Research and Planning, contain information on administration, enrollment trends, student and faculty characteristics, admission trends, program enrollments, degrees conferred, and alumni distribution in Connecticut.
Arrangement
Arranged in alphabetical and chronological order.
The files are grouped into 11 series:
Missing Title
Board of Trustees, 1984-1998 (w/gaps)
Chancellor's Office, 1990-1998
Office of the President, 1985, 1994
Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs and Research, 1988, 2002
Office of Finance and Management, 1989-1997 (w/gaps)
Office of Institutional Research and Planning, 1965-1999 (w/gaps)
Connecticut State University System Foundation, 1990-2002
Connecticut State University System Research Foundation, 1986-1987
Office of Public Relations, 1968-2000 (w/gaps)
Connecticut State University System Publications, 1968-2003
University Wide Committee on the Arts, 1988-2002 (w/gaps)
Calendars.; Fliers (printed matter); Agendas; Postcards; Universities and colleges -- Connecticut -- Finance.; Directories.; Invitations.; Pamphlets.; Publications.; Reports.; State universities and colleges -- Connecticut.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Universities and colleges -- Administration.; Connecticut State University (System) -- Research Foundation.; Connecticut State University (System) -- Foundation.; Cibes, Jr., William J.; Beal, Dallas K.; Western Connecticut State University; Connecticut State University (System).; Western Connecticut State University. University Wide Committee on the Arts.
- 1. Board of Trustees, 1984-1998
  - Agenda, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Agenda Summary, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mission Statements, 1984, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Newsletter, No. 3, Jan 29, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Policy Book, 1983-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12-24)
  - Policy Book, Version 1.1, Aug 1998 (Box 1, Folder 25-30)
  - Policy Book, Version 1.1 (c.2), Aug 1998 (Box 1, Folder 31-36)
  - Policy Book, Addendum, 1983-1993 (Box 1, Folder 37-50)
  - Parking Garage and Associated Site Improvements, WCSU, Midtown Campus, Draft: July 2005, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Phase I Archaeological Reconnaissance Survey, Westside Campus, WCSU, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 66-67)
- 2. Chancellor, 1992-1998
  - William J. Cibes, Jr., 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Governor's Budget Recommendations, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 51A)
  - Education that works for Connecticut - Governmental Relations, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Public Acts of Significance - Governmental Relations, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Public Acts of Significance - Governmental Relations, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 54-55)
  - Public Acts of Significance - Governmental Relations, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Public Acts of Significance - Governmental Relations, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Public Acts of Significance - Governmental Relations (c.2), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Public Acts of Significance - Governmental Relations (c.2), 1998 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Assessment of Management Information Systems - Strategic Planning, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Assessment of Administrative Processes, Final Report - Strategic Planning, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence - Strategic Planning, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 62-63)
  - Eastern Connecticut State University - Strategic Planning, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Presentation to Rating Agencies - Strategic Planning, Oct 3, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 65-66)
  - David G. Carter, Sr., 2006 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- 3. Office of the President
  - Dallas K. Beal, 1985, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1a)
  - Frost, Dr. James A., 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1b)
- 4. Office of the V. P. for Academic Affairs and Research
  - Directory of Faculty Scholarly & Research Expertise, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 5. Office of Finance and Management, 1989-1997
  - Access and Excellence, FY95-97, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Access and Excellence, FY95-97(c.2), 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Finance, Administration & Development Committee Meetings, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6-11)
  - Financial Report, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Financial Statements and Schedules, 1988; "With Comparative Amounts for 1987" "With Independent Auditors' Report" (Box 2, Folder 13.1)
  - Financial Statements and Schedules, 1994; "With Independent Auditors' Report" (Box 2, Folder 13.2)
  - FY 1994-95 Financial Report, Jul 1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - FY 1997-98 Spending Plans (Box 2, Folder 15-19)
  - Internal Audit & Audit Committee Report, March 2, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Requested Operating Budget, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- 6. Office of Institutional Research and Planning, 1965-1999
  - Fact Book, Four College, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Fact Book, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Fact Book, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 23A)
  - Fact Book, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fact Book, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Fact Book, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Fact Book, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Fact Book, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 27A)
  - Fact Book, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Fact Book, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Fact Book, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Fact Book, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Fact Book, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Report on the Governor's Commission on Higher Education and the Economy, January 1982 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Faculty Salary Study, Jan.1993 (Box 2, Folder 33A)
- 7. Connecticut State University Foundation, 1990-2002
  - Invitations, 1990-2002 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Henry Barnard Distinguished Lectureship, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 68)
- 8. Connecticut State University Research Foundation, 1986-1987
  - The CSURF Report, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The CSURF Report, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- 9. Office of Public Relations, 1992-2004
  - Pamphlets, 1992-1997 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Pamphlets, 1999-2003 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Pamphlets, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - We Are Four, We Are One, 1983-2008 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- 10. CSUS Publications, 1968-2003
  - CSC Newsletter, 1968, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - CSU News, 1991-1994 (Box OS 1)
  - CSU Today, 1995-1997 (Box OS 1)
  - CSUS Today, 1998-1999 (Box OS 1)
  - Directions, CSU at Waterbury, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Profiles on Student Health: 2000 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Quality Report, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Quality Report, 1998-2000 (Box OS 1)
  - Universe, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Universe, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
  - Universe, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
  - Universe, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 50-51)
  - Universe, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 52-53)
  - Universe, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Universe, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Universe, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Universe, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Universe, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Universe, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Universe, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Universe, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - WebCT Vista Project, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- 11. University Wide Committee on the Arts, 1988-2002
  - Flyers and calendars, 1988-1999 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Flyers and calendars, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 60)